Sometimes, I think I'm cursed.
Je crois parfois ךtre victime d'une malיdiction
Because of something that happened before I was even born.
א cause d'une chose qui s'est passיe avant ma naissance.
See, a long time ago, there was this family.
Il יtait une fois une famille.
The papa, he was a musician.
Le papב יtait musicien.
He and his family would sing and dance and count their blessings.
Sa famille et lui chantaient, dansaient et יtaient choyיs par la vie.
But he also had a dream. To play for the world.
Mais il avait aussi un rךve : jouer pour le monde entier.
And one day, he left with his guitar and never returned.
Un jour, il est parti avec sa guitare et n'est jamais revenu.
And the mamé...
Et la mamב...
She didn't have time to cry over that walk—away musician.
Elle n'a pas perdu son temps א pleurer ce vaurien.
After banishing all music from her life she found a way...
Aprטs avoir banni la musique de sa vie, elle a trouvי un moyen
to provide for her daughter.
de subvenir aux besoins de sa fille.
She rolled up her sleeves and she learned to make shoes.
Elle s'est retroussי les manches et a appris א fabriquer des chaussures.
She could have made candy, or ﬁreworks, or sparkly unden/vear...
Elle aurait pu fabriquer des bonbons, des feux d'artifice ou des caleחons
for wrestlers, but no, she chose shoes.
א paillettes pour les lutteurs, mais non, elle a choisi les chaussures.
Then she taught her daughter to make shoes.
Elle a enseignי א sa fille א en fabriquer aussi.
And later, she taught her son—in—law.
Et plus tard, א son gendre.
Then her grandkids got roped in.
Ensuite, les petits-enfants ont יtי recrutיs.
As her family grew, so did the business.
Son entreprise grandissait au mךme rythme que sa famille.
Music had torn her family apart.
La musique avait dיchirי cette famille,
But shoes held them all together.
mais les chaussures la gardaient unie.
You see, that woman was my great- great—grandmother, Mamé Imelda.
Cette femme, c'יtait mamב Imelda, mon arriטre-arriטre-grand-mטre.
She died way before I was born.
Elle est morte longtemps avant que je naisse.
But my family still tells her story every year on Dia de los Muertos...
Mais ma famille raconte son histoire chaque Dםa de los Muertos,
the Day of the Dead.
le jour des ancךtres.
And her little girl, she's my great—grandmother, Mamé Coco.
Sa fille, c'יtait mon arriטre-grand-mטre, mamב Coco.
Hola, Mama’ Coco.
Hola, mamב Coco.
How are you, Julio?
Comment vas-tu, Julio ?
Actually, my name is Miguel.
En fait, je m'appelle Miguel.
Mama Coco has trouble remembering things.
Mamב Coco a des trous de mיmoire.
But it's good to talk to her anyway. So, I tell her pretty much everything.
J'aime quand mךme lui parler. Je lui raconte pratiquement tout.
I used to run like this. But now I run like this which is way faster.
Avant, je courais comme חa. Mais je suis devenu bien plus rapide.
I have a dimple on this side, but not on this side.
J'ai une fossette ici, mais pas lא.
Dimple, no dimple. Dimple, no dimple.
Fossette, pas de fossette.
Miguel, eat your food.
Miguel, vide ton assiette.
My abuelita, she's Mama Coco's daughter.
Mon abuelita est la fille de mamב Coco.
Oh, you're a twig, mijo. Have some more.
Tu es tout maigrichon, mijo. Prends-en encore.
No, gracias.
Non, gracias.
I asked if you would like more tamalesl
Je t'ai demandי si tu voulais encore des tamales !
Si?
Sם ?
That's what I thought you said!
C'est bien ce que je croyais !
No music!
Pas de musique !
-Y aunque la vida -No music!
- Y aunque la vida - Pas de musique !
I think we're the only family in México who hates music.
On est la seule famille au Mexique א dיtester la musique, je crois bien.
And my family's ﬁne with that. But me...
Le reste de la famille accepte חa, mais moi...
-Be back by lunch, mijo. —Love you, Mama.
- Reviens pour dמner, mijo. - Je t'aime, mamב.
I am not like the rest of my family!
Je ne suis pas comme le reste de ma famille !
-Muchas gracias. -De nada, Miguel.
- Muchas gracias. - De nada, Miguel.
Hey! Dante!
Hי ! Dante !
Sit. Down. Roll over. Shake.
Assis. Couchי. Roule. Remue-toi.
Fist bump!
Tope lא !
Good boy, Dante!
Bon chien, Dante !
I know I'm not supposed to love music.
Je sais que je ne suis pas censי aimer la musique.
But it's not my fault! It's his!
Mais ce n'est pas ma faute ! C'est la sienne !
Ernesto de la Cruz. The greatest musician of all time.
Ernesto de la Cruz. Le plus grand musicien de l'histoire.
Right here in this very plaza, Ernesto de la Cruz took his first steps...
C'est sur cette place publique qu'Ernesto de la Cruz a fait ses dיbuts
toward becoming the most beloved singer in Mexican history.
pour devenir le chanteur le plus adulי de l'histoire du Mexique.
But when he played music, he made people fall in love with him.
Mais quand il jouait de la musique, les gens se pגmaient pour lui.
He starred in movies.
Il tenait la vedette dans des films.
He had the coolest guitar! He could ﬂy!
Il avait la guitare la plus chouette ! Il pouvait voler !
And he wrote the best songs.
Et il composait les meilleures chansons.
But my all—time favorite, it's...
Ma prיfיrיe de tous les temps, c'est...
-Remember me
- Ne m'oublie pas
Though I have to say goodbye
Je vais devoir m'en aller
Don't let it make you cry For even if I'm far away
Tu ne dois pas pleurer Mךme si je suis trטs loin de toi
I hold you in my heart I sing a secret song to you
Tu restes dans mon cur Je chante en secret chaque soir
Each night we are apart Remember me
Pour que tu n'aies plus peur Ne m'oublie pas
Though I have to travel far
C'est א regret que je pars
-Remember me
- Ne m'oublie pas
Each time you hear a sad guitar
Quand tu entendras une guitare
Know that I'm with you the only way that I can be
Tu ne me vois pas Pourtant je suis tout prטs de toi
Until you're in my arms again
Quand je chante Tu es dans mes bras
Until 1942.
Jusqu'en 1942.
When he was crushed by a giant bell.
C'est alors qu'il fut יcrabouillי par une cloche gיante.
I want to be just like him.
Je veux devenir exactement comme lui.
Sometimes, I look at de la Cruz and I get this feeling like we're connected.
Parfois, quand je regarde de la Cruz, je sens qu'un lien nous unit.
Like if he could play music, maybe someday, I could too.
S'il a pu jouer de la musique, peut-ךtre que moi aussi, j'y arriverai.
If it wasn't for my family.
Si ce n'יtait pas de ma famille.
-Ay-ay-ay, muchacho. -Huh?
- Ay-ay-ay, muchacho. - Hein ?
I asked for a shoe shine not your life story.
Cire mes chaussures au lieu de raconter ta vie.
Oh, yeah. Sorry.
Ah, oui. Excusez-moi.
I just can't really talk about any of this at home. So...
C'est juste que je ne peux parler de rien de חa א la maison, alors...
If I were you, I'd march right up to my family and say...
ְ ta place, j'irais voir ma famille et je dirais :
"Hey, I'm a musician. Deal with it."
"Je suis musicien. Acceptez-le."
—I could never say that. —You are a musician, no?
- Je ne pourrais jamais dire חa. - Tu es musicien, non ?
I don't know. I mean, I only really play for myself.
Je ne sais pas trop. Je ne joue que pour moi-mךme.
Did de la Cruz become the world's best musician by hiding his skills’?
De la Cruz est-il devenu le meilleur au monde en cachant son talent ?
No! He walked out onto that plaza and he played out loud.
Non ! Il s'est rendu sur la place et il a jouי bien fort.
Mira, mira, they're setting up for tonight!
Mira, mira, ils se prיparent pour ce soir !
The music competition for Dla de Muertos.
Le concours du Dםa de Muertos.
You want to be like your hero? You should sign up!
PLAZA SANTA CECILIA - 7PM
Uh—uh. My family would freak!
Non. Ma famille ferait une crise !
Look, if you're too scared then, well, have fun making shoes.
Si tu as trop peur, il te reste א fabriquer des chaussures.
Come on, what did de la Cruz always say?
Que disait toujours de la Cruz ?
Seize your moment?
Saisis ton moment ?
Show me what you got, muchacho.
Montre-moi ce que tu sais faire, muchacho.
I'll be your first audience.
Je serai ton premier spectateur.
Miguel!
Miguel !
-Abuelita! —What are you doing here?
- Abuelita ! - Que fais-tu lא ?
You leave my grandson alone.
Laisse mon petit-fils tranquille.
Doﬁa, please! Iwasjust getting a shine.
Doסa, voyons ! Je faisais cirer mes chaussures.
I know your tricks, mariachi. What did he say to you?
Je connais tes astuces, mariachi. Que t'a-t-il dit ?
He was just showing me his guitar.
Il m'a montrי sa guitare, c'est tout.
Shame on you.
Tu devrais avoir honte.
My grandson is a sweet little angelito querido cielito.
Mon petit-fils est un gentil petit angelito querido cielito.
He wants no part of your music, mariachi. You keep away from him.
Il ne s'intיresse pas א ta musique, mariachi. Tiens-toi loin de lui.
Ay, pobrecito. Oh, estas bien, mijo.
Ay, pobrecito. Estבs bien, mijo.
You know better than to be here in this place!
Tu sais bien que tu ne devrais pas traמner ici !
You will come home. Now.
Rentre א la maison. Tout de suite.
How many times have we told you? That plaza is crawling with mariachis.
Combien de fois faut-il te le rיpיter ? Cette place grouille de mariachis.
Yes, Tio Berto.
Oui, tםo Berto.
-No, no, no, no, no! —Go away, you. Go!
- Non, non, non. - Fiche le camp. Ouste !
It's just Dante.
Ce n'est que Dante.
Never name a street dog. They'll follow you forever. Now, go get my shoe.
Ne t'attache pas aux chiens errants. Va chercher ma sandale.
I found your son in Mariachi Plaza.
J'ai trouvי ton fils א la place des mariachis.
AM Miguel!
Ay, Miguel !
You know how Abuelita feels about the plaza.
Tu sais ce qu'abuelita pense de cette place.
-I was just shining shoes. -A musician's shoes!
- Je cirais des chaussures. - Celles d'un musicien !
But the plaza's where all the foot traffic is.
C'est א la place qu'on trouve le plus de clients.
If Abuelita says no more plaza, then no more plaza.
Si abuelita dit de ne plus y aller, alors tu n'y vas plus.
-But what about tonight? —What's tonight?
- Mais, ce soir ? - Quoi, ce soir ?
Well, they're having this talent show. And Ithought I might...
Il y a un concours d'amateurs. Je pensais que je pourrais...
—Sign up? —well, maybe?
- T'inscrire ? - Peut-ךtre ?
You have to have talent to be in a talent show.
Qu'irais-tu faire lא ? Tu n'as aucun talent.
What are you gonna do? Shine shoes?
Tu ferais quoi ? Cirer des chaussures ?
It's Dla de los Muertos.
C'est le Dםa de los Muertos.
No one's going anywhere. Tonight is about family.
Personne n'ira nulle part. Ce soir, on reste en famille.
Ofrenda room. Va’monos.
La salle d'ofrenda. Vבmonos.
Don't give me that look.
Ne me regarde pas comme חa.
Dia de los Muertos is the one night of the year
Le Dםa de los Muertos est le seul soir de l'annיe oש on reחoit les ancךtres.
We've put their photos on the ofrenda so their spirits can cross over.
On a exposי leur photo sur l'ofrenda pour aider le passage des esprits.
That is very important.
C'est trטs important.
If we don't put them up, they can't come.
Si on n'expose pas leur photo, ils ne pourront pas venir.
We made all this food, set out the things they loved in life, mijo.
On a prיparי de la nourriture et sorti les objets qu'ils aimaient.
All this work to bring the family together.
Tout חa pour rassembler la famille.
I don't want you sneaking off to who knows where. Where are you going?
Pas question que tu sortes en cachette. Oש vas-tu ?
I thought we were done.
Je croyais qu'on avait fini.
Ay, Dios mio. Being part of this family means being here for this family.
Ay, Dios mםo. Tu fais partie de la famille. Tu dois ךtre lא.
-I don't want to see you end up Iike-- -Like Mama’ Coco's papa’?
- Je ne veux pas que tu finisses... - Comme le papב de mamב Coco ?
Never mention that man! He's better off forgotten.
Ne mentionne jamais cet homme ! Mieux vaut l'oublier.
But you're the one who——
Mais c'est toi qui...
I was just——
Je disais juste...
But-- I--
Mais... Je...
Papa? Papa is home?
Papב ? Papב est revenu ?
Mama’, calmese, calmese.
Mamב, cבlmese, cבlmese.
Papa’ is coming home?
Papב va revenir א la maison ?
Who are you?
Qui es-tu ?
Rest, Mama.
Repose-toi, mamב.
I'm hard on you because I care, Miguel. Miguel? Miguel?
Si je te fais la vie dure, Miguel, c'est que je me soucie de toi. Miguel ?
What are we going to do with that boy?
Qu'allons-nous faire de ce garחon ?
You're right. That's just what he needs.
Tu as raison. C'est en plein ce qu'il lui faut.
It's you. Get in here. Come on, Dante. Hurry up!
C'est toi. Monte. Viens, Dante. Vite !
You're gonna get me in trouble, boy. Someone could hear me.
Tu vas me mettre dans le pיtrin. Quelqu'un pourrait m'entendre.
I wish someone wanted to hear me.
J'aimerais que quelqu'un veuille m'entendre.
Other than you. Ew. Okay.
ְ part toi. Beurk ! Bon.
Perfecto!
Perfecto !
I have to sing. I have to play!
Je dois chanter. Je dois jouer !
The music, it's not just in me, it is me.
La musique n'est pas seulement en moi. Elle est moi.
When life gets me down, I play my guitar.
Quand je me sens abattu, je joue de la guitare.
The rest of the world may follow the rules, but I must follow my heart.
Le reste du monde suit les rטgles, mais moi, je suis mon cur.
You know that feeling like there's a song in the air and...
Tu connais ce sentiment. Il y a une mיlodie dans l'air
it's playing just for you?
et elle ne joue que pour toi.
A feeling so close...
D'un regard effacer
you could reach out and touch it
Toutes les douleurs du passי
I never knew I could want something so much, but it's true
Les rךves s'envolent et reviennent Encore plus forts et plus beaux
You must have faith, sister.
Ayez la foi, ma sur.
Oh, but, Padre, he will never listen.
Mais padre, il n'יcoute jamais.
He will listen. To music.
Il יcoutera la musique.
Only a song, only a song has the power to change a heart
Seule une chanson a le pouvoir De changer les curs
Never underestimate the power of music.
Ne sous-estime jamais le pouvoir de la musique.
But my father, he will never give his permission.
Mon pטre n'accordera jamais sa permission.
I am done asking permission.
J'en ai assez de demander la permission.
When you see your moment, you mustn't let it pass you by.
Quand vient le moment, il ne faut pas le laisser passer.
You must seize it!
Il faut le saisir !
Seﬁor de la Cruz, what did it take for you to seize your moment?
Seסor de la Cruz, qu'a-t-il fallu pour que vous saisissiez votre moment ?
I had to have faith in my dream. No one was going to hand it to me.
J'ai cru en mon rךve. Personne n'allait le rיaliser pour moi.
It was up to me to reach for that dream.
C'יtait א moi de suivre ce rךve.
—Grab it tight and make it come true. -...and make it come true.
- De le saisir et de le rיaliser. - ... et de le rיaliser.
No more hiding, Dante. I got to seize my moment!
J'ai fini de me cacher, Dante. Je vais saisir mon moment !
I'm gonna play in Mariachi Plaza if it kills me.
Je jouerai א la place des mariachis cote que cote.
Dia de los Muertos has begun!
Le Dםa de los Muertos a commencי !
No, no. We have to make a clear path.
Non, non. Le chemin doit ךtre bien tracי.
The petals guide our ancestors home. We don't want their spirits to get lost.
Les pיtales guident nos ancךtres. Leur esprit ne doit pas se perdre.
We want them to come and enjoy all the food and drinks on the ofrenda.
Ils doivent venir dיguster la nourriture et les boissons de l'ofrenda.
Mama! Where should we put this table?
Mamב ! Oש veux-tu cette table ?
In the courtyard, mr'jos.
Dans la cour, mijos.
-You want it down by the kitchen? -SI. Next to the other one.
- Prטs de la cuisine ? - Sם. ְ cפtי de l'autre.
—Get under! Get under! -Miguel?
- Cache-toi dessous ! - Miguel ?
Nothing! Mama, Papa. I--
Rien ! Mamב, papב. Je...
Miguel, your abuelita had the most wonderful idea.
Miguel, ton abuelita a eu une merveilleuse idיe.
We've all decided. It's time you joined us in the workshop!
On est tous d'accord. Tu vas te joindre א nous dans l'atelier !
What?
- Quoi ? - Fini, le cirage de chaussures.
You'll be making them every day after school.
Tu en fabriqueras tous les jours aprטs l'יcole.
Oh! Our MigueIi—ti—ti—ti—to carrying on the family tradition.
Oh ! Notre Migueli-ti-ti-ti-to va continuer la tradition familiale !
And on Dia de los Muertos! Your ancestors will be so proud.
En plein Dםa de los Muertos ! Tes ancךtres seront si fiers.
You'll craft huaraches just like your Tia Victoria.
Tu fabriqueras des sandales, comme tםa Victoria.
And wingtips like your Papa Julio.
Et des richelieus, comme papב Julio.
Ah, Miguel. You have your family here to guide you.
Ah, Miguel. Ta famille sera lא pour te guider.
You are a Rivera. And a Rivera is...
Tu es un Rivera. Et un Rivera est...
A shoemaker. Through and through.
Un fabricant de chaussures. De la tךte aux pieds.
That's my boy! Berto!
Viens lא, fiston ! Berto !
Break out the good stuff. I want to make a toast.
Sors une bonne bouteille. Je veux porter un toast.
Dante! No, Dante. Stop!
Dante ! Non, Dante. Arrךte !
No, no, no, no, no! No.
Non, non, non ! Non.
De la Cruz's guitar?
La guitare de de la Cruz ?
Papa ? Papa?
Papב ? Papב ?
Mama Coco, is your papa Ernesto de la Cruz?
Mamב Coco, ton papב יtait-il Ernesto de la Cruz ?
Papa! Papa!
Papב ! Papב !
Papa! Papa! It's him!
Papב ! Papב ! C'est lui !
Miguel, get down from there.
Miguel, descends de lא.
Mama Coco's father was Ernesto de la Cruz!
Le pטre de mamב Coco יtait Ernesto de la Cruz !
—What are you talking about? -I'm gonna be a musician!
- Qu'est-ce que tu racontes ? - Je deviendrai musicien !
What is all this? You keep secrets from your own family?
C'est quoi, tout חa ? Tu caches des choses א ta famille ?
It's all that time he spends in the plaza.
C'est א cause du temps qu'il passe א la place.
—Fills his head with crazy fantasies. —It's not a fantasy.
- Il a la tךte pleine d'illusions. - Ce n'est pas une illusion.
That man was Ernesto de la Cruz! The greatest musician of all time!
Cet homme יtait Ernesto de la Cruz ! Le plus grand musicien de l'histoire !
We've never known anything about this man!
On ne sait rien de cet homme !
But whoever he was, he still abandoned his family.
Peu importe qui il יtait, il a abandonnי sa famille.
This is no future for my son.
Mon fils ne suivra pas ses traces.
But, Papa, you said my family would guide me.
Mais papב, tu as dit que ma famille me guiderait.
Well, de la Cruz is my family.
De la Cruz fait partie de ma famille.
I'm supposed to play music.
Je suis censי jouer de la musique.
Never! That man's music was a curse. Iwill not allow it.
Jamais ! La musique de cet homme יtait une malיdiction. Je l'interdis.
—If you would just |et—— -Miguel...
- Si tu me laissais... - Miguel...
You will listen to your family. No more music.
ֹcoute ta famille. C'est fini, la musique.
—Just listen to me play! —End of argument.
- Mais יcoutez-moi jouer ! - Fin de la discussion.
You want to end up like that man? Forgotten?
Tu veux finir comme lui ? Oubliי ?
Left off your family's ofrenda?
Exclu de l'ofrenda de ta famille ?
I don't care if I'm on some stupid ofrenda.
Je me fiche d'ךtre sur une ofrenda idiote.
-No! -Mama!
- Non ! - Mamב !
There. No guitar. No music.
Et voilא. Plus de guitare, plus de musique.
Oh, come. You'll feel better after you eat with your family.
Viens. Tu te sentiras mieux quand tu auras mangי avec ta famille.
I don't want to be in this family!
Je ne veux rien savoir de cette famille !
Miguel! Miguel!
Miguel ! Miguel !
I want to play in the plaza, like de la Cruz. Can I still sign up?
Je veux jouer sur la place comme de la Cruz. Je peux m'inscrire ?
You got an instrument?
As-tu un instrument ?
Musicians got to bring their own instruments.
Les musiciens apportent leurs instruments.
You find a guitar, kid, I'll put you on the list.
Si tu trouves une guitare, petit, je t'inscrirai.
-Can I borrow your guitar? —Sorry, muchacho.
- Puis-je emprunter votre guitare ? - Je regrette, muchacho.
-You guys have a spare guitar? -No.
- Auriez-vous une guitare en trop ? - Non.
—I need a guitarjust for a little bit. —Get out of here, kid.
- J'ai besoin d'une guitare un moment. - Dיgage, petit.
Great—great—grandfather, what am I supposed to do?
Arriטre-arriטre-grand-pטre, que suis-je censי faire ?
No, no, no, no. Dante, stop! Callatel Sh!
Non, non, non. Dante, arrךte ! Cבllate ! Chut !
I'm sorry.
Je suis navrי.
Senor de la Cruz, please don't be mad. I'm Miguel.
Seסor de la Cruz, ne vous fגchez pas. Je m'appelle Miguel.
Your great-great grandson. I need to borrow this.
Je suis votre arriטre-arriטre-petit-fils. Je dois vous emprunter חa.
Our family thinks music is a curse.
Notre famille croit que la musique est une malיdiction.
None of them understand but I know you would have.
Je sais que contrairement א elle, vous auriez compris.
You would have told me to follow my heart. To seize my moment!
Vous m'auriez dit de suivre mon cur. De saisir mon moment !
So, if it's all right with you, I'm gonna play in the plaza. Just like you did!
Si vous le permettez, je jouerai sur la place, comme vous !
The guitar! It's gone!
La guitare ! Elle a disparu !
Somebody stole de la Cruz's guitar!
Quelqu'un a volי la guitare de de la Cruz !
The window's broken. Look!
La fenךtre est brisיe. Regardez !
All right, who's in there?
Qui est lא ?
I'm sorry. It's not what it looks like. De la Cruz is my—-
Ce n'est pas ce que vous croyez. De la Cruz est mon...
There's nobody here.
Il n'y a personne ici.
-Miguel! -Mama!
- Miguel ! - Mamב !
Miguel, come home. Where are you, Miguel?
Miguel, reviens א la maison. Oש es-tu, Miguel ?
Dios mio! Little boy. Are you okay? Here. Let me help you.
Dios mםo ! Tu n'as rien, petit ? Je vais t'aider.
Thanks. I--
Merci. Je...
Do you mind? Whoa!
Ne te gךne surtout pas ! Oh !
Look how big she's getting.
Regarde comme elle a grandi.
Dante!
Dante !
You can see me? Wait! What's going on? Dante!
Tu peux me voir ? Attends ! Que se passe-t-il ? Dante !
Oh, I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
Excusez-moi.
Miguel?
Miguel ?
-Miguel?
- Miguel ?
You're here? Here, here. And you can see us?
Tu es ici ? Ici mךme. Et tu nous vois ?
Our Migueli-ti-ti-ti-to!
Notre Migueli-ti-ti-ti-to !
Remind me how I know you.
Rappelez-moi... On se connaמt ?
We're your family, mr'jo.
On est ta famille, mijo.
-Tia Rosita? -Si.
- Tםa Rosita ? - Sם.
-Papa Julio? -Hola,
- Papב Julio ? - Hola.
Tr’a Victoria?
Tםa Victoria ?
He doesn't seem entirely dead.
Il n'a pas l'air tout א fait mort.
He's not quite alive either.
Il n'est pas tout א fait vivant non plus.
We need Mama Imelda. She'll know how to fix this.
Allons chercher mamב Imelda. Elle saura comment rיgler חa.
Oye! It's Mama Imelda.
Oye ! C'est א propos de mamב Imelda.
-She's stuck! -On the other side!
- Elle est coincיe ! - De l'autre cפtי !
Tio Oscar? Tio Felipe?
Tםo Oscar ? Tםo Felipe ?
Oh. Hey, Miguel.
Salut, Miguel.
I have a feeling this has something to do with you.
J'ai le sentiment que tu as quelque chose א y voir.
But if Mama’ Imelda can't come to us...
Mais si mamב Imelda ne vient pas jusqu'א nous...
Then we are going to her. Vamonos!
Nous irons jusqu'א elle. Vבmonos !
Come on, Miguel. It's okay.
Viens, Miguel. ַa ira.
Dante? Dante! Dante, wait up!
Dante ? Dante ! Dante, attends !
You got to stay with me, boy. We don't know... where...
Reste avec moi, mon chien. On ne sait pas oש...
This isn't a dream then. You're all really out there.
Ce n'est donc pas un rךve. Vous ךtes vraiment tous ici.
-You thought we weren't? -Well, I don't know.
- Tu n'y croyais pas ? - Je ne sais pas.
I thought it might've been one of those made up things that adults tell kids.
Je croyais que c'יtait un truc inventי qu'on raconte aux enfants.
-Like vitamins. -Miguel, vitamins are a real thing.
- Comme les vitamines. - Miguel, les vitamines existent.
Well, now I'm thinking maybe they could be.
Je commence א croire que c'est possible.
Mija, it's not nice to stare at-- Ay! Santa Maria!
Mija, ce n'est pas poli de fixer... Ay ! Santa Maria !
Are those... Alebrijes! But those are--
Est-ce... Des alebrijes ! Mais c'est...
Real alebrijes. Spirit creatures.
De vrais alebrijes. Des crיatures spirituelles.
They guide souls on theirjourney.
Ils guident les גmes durant leur voyage.
Watch your step. They make caquitas everywhere.
Regarde oש tu marches. Ils font caca partout.
Welcome back to the Land of the Dead.
Bon retour dans le monde des ancךtres.
Please have all offerings ready for re—entry.
Veuillez prיparer vos offrandes.
Welcome back. Anything to declare?
Bon retour. Quelque chose א dיclarer ?
Some churros. From my family.
Des churros. De ma famille.
How wonderful. Next.
Merveilleux. Suivant.
If you are experiencing travel issues, agents at the Department of Family...
Un problטme de voyage ? Les agents du ministטre des Retrouvailles
Reunions are available to assist you.
familiales sont lא pour vous aider.
Next family, please.
Famille suivante.
Oh! Your photos are on your son's ofrenda. Have a great visit.
Vos photos sont sur l'ofrenda de votre fils. Bonne visite.
Gracias.
Gracias.
And remember to return before sunrise. Enjoy your visit.
N'oubliez pas de rentrer avant l'aurore. Bonne visite.
Next. Your photo's on your dentist's ofrenda. Enjoy your visit.
Votre photo est sur l'ofrenda de votre dentiste. Bonne visite.
-Gracias. -Next?
- Gracias. - Suivant ?
Yes! It is I. Frida Kahlo.
Oui ! C'est moi. Frida Kahlo.
Shall we skip the scanner?
Peut-on sauter le balayage ?
I'm on so many ofrendas it'll just ovenrvhelm your blinky thingy.
Je suis sur tant d'ofrendas que חa va dיtraquer votre machine.
Well, shoot, looks like no one put up your photo, Frida.
Personne n'a exposי votre photo, Frida.
Okay, when I said Iwas Frida, just now, that was a lie.
Bon, quand j'ai dit que j'יtais Frida, c'יtait un mensonge.
And I apologize for doing that.
Excusez-moi.
No photo on an ofrenda, no crossing the bridge.
Pas de photo sur une ofrenda, pas de passage.
I'm just gonna zip right over. You won't even know I'm gone.
Je vais juste faire un petit tour. Mon absence passera inaperחue.
Hey!
Hי !
A|most...there. Just a little further.
J'y suis... presque. Juste un peu plus loin.
Ulosy-daisy_._
Allez, debout.
Fine. Okay. Fine, who cares? Dumb flower bridge!
C'est bon. On s'en fiche. C'est un ridicule pont en fleurs !
Aw. I don't know what I'd do if no one put up my photo.
J'ignore ce que je ferais si personne n'exposait ma photo.
-Next? -Oh! Come, mr'jo. It's ourturn.
- Suivant ? - Viens, mijo. C'est א notre tour.
Welcome back, amigos. Anything to declare?
Bon retour, amigos. Quelque chose א dיclarer ?
As a matter of fact, yes.
ְ vrai dire, oui.
Paging Marta Gonzales-Ramos. Please report to Level Seven.
On demande Marta Gonzales-Ramos au septiטme יtage.
I miss my nose.
Mon nez me manque.
Come on, help us out, amigo. We got to get to a dozen ofrendas tonight.
Aidez-nous donc, amigo. On a une dizaine d'ofrendas א visiter.
We are not visiting your ex-wife's family for Dia de Muertos!
On n'ira pas voir la famille de ton ex pour le Dםa de Muertos !
I demand to speak to the person in charge!
J'exige de parler א un responsable !
I'm sorry, seﬁora, it says here no one put up your photo.
Je regrette, seסora, mais personne n'a exposי votre photo.
My family always puts my photo on the ofrenda.
Ma famille expose toujours ma photo sur l'ofrenda.
That devil box tells you nothing but lies!
Cette boמte diabolique ne raconte que des mensonges !
-Mama Imelda? -Oh, mi familial
- Mamב Imelda ? - Oh, mi familia !
They wouldn't let me cross the bridge.
Ils m'ont empךchיe de traverser.
Tell this woman and her devil box that my photo is on the ofrenda.
Dites א cette femme et א sa boמte que ma photo est sur l'ofrenda.
Well, we never made it to the ofrenda.
On ne s'est jamais rendus א l'ofrenda.
-What? -We ran into...
- Quoi ? - On est tombיs sur...
-Miguel? -Mama Imelda.
- Miguel ? - Mamב Imelda.
What is going on?
Que se passe-t-il ?
You the Rivera family?
Vous ךtes la famille Rivera ?
-Well, you're cursed. -What?
- Vous ךtes maudits. - Quoi ?
Dla de los Muertos is the night to give to the dead. You stole from the dead!
Lors du Dםa de los Muertos, on donne aux morts. On ne vole pas !
-But I wasn't stealing the guitar. -Guitar?
- Je n'ai pas volי la guitare. - La guitare ?
It was my great-great-grandfather's. He would have wanted me to have it.
Mon arriטre-arriטre-grand-pטre aurait voulu que je l'aie.
We do not speak of that musician. He is dead to this family.
On ne parle pas du musicien. Il est mort aux yeux de la famille.
You're all dead.
Vous ךtes tous morts.
I am sorry. Whose alebrije is that?
Excusez-moi. ְ qui est cet alebrije ?
That's just Dante.
Ce n'est que Dante.
He sure doesn't look like an alebrije.
On ne dirait pas un alebrije.
He just looks like a plain old dog.
On dirait un chien ordinaire.
Or a sausage someone dropped in a barbershop.
Ou une saucisse יchappיe chez le barbier.
Whatever he is, I am terribly allergic.
Peu importe, je suis terriblement allergique.
But Dante doesn't have any hair.
Dante n'a mךme pas de poil.
And I don't have a nose, and yet, here we are.
Je n'ai mךme pas de nez, et pourtant, c'est comme חa.
But none of this explains why I couldn't cross over.
ַa n'explique pas ce qui a empךchי mon passage.
Oh!
Oh !
You took my photo off the ofrenda?
Tu as enlevי ma photo de l'ofrenda ?
-It was an accident! -How do we send him back?
- C'יtait un accident ! - Comment le renvoyer ?
Well, since it's a family matter...
Comme c'est une affaire de famille...
the way to undo a family curse is to get your family's blessing.
Pour rompre la malיdiction, il faut une bיnיdiction familiale.
That's it?
C'est tout ?
Get your family's blessing and everything should go back to normal.
Avec la bיnיdiction de ta famille, tout devrait rentrer dans l'ordre.
But you got to do it by sunrise.
Mais ce doit ךtre fait d'ici l'aurore.
What happens at sunrise?
Que se passera-t-il א l'aurore ?
Hijolel Your hand!
Hםjole ! Ta main !
Whoa, Miguel, can't have you fainting on us.
Allons, Miguel, ne t'יvanouis pas.
But not to worry. Your family's here. You can get your blessing right now.
Ne t'inquiטte pas. Ta famille est lא. Tu peux obtenir ta bיnיdiction.
Cempasuchil, cempasuchil. Aha! Perdon, seriora.
Cempasתchil, cempasתchil. Ah-ha ! Perdףn, seסora.
Now, you look at the living and say his name.
Regardez le vivant et dites son nom.
Miguel.
Miguel.
Nailed it. Now say, "I give you my blessing."
Parfait. Maintenant, dites : "Je t'accorde ma bיnיdiction."
I give you my blessing.
Je t'accorde ma bיnיdiction.
I give you my blessing to go home...
Je t'accorde ma bיnיdiction pour que tu rentres chez toi,
to put my photo back on the ofrenda, and to never play music again.
remettes ma photo sur l'ofrenda et ne joues plus jamais de musique.
Well, technically, she can add any condition she wants.
En principe, elle peut ajouter toutes les conditions qu'elle veut.
-Fine. -Then you hand the petal to Miguel.
- Trטs bien. - Donnez le pיtale א Miguel.
No skeletons!
Pas de squelettes !
Mariachi Plaza, here I come.
Place des mariachis, me voici.
Two seconds and you already break your promise.
Deux secondes et tu romps dיjא ta promesse.
This isn't fair. It's my life. You already had yours.
Ce n'est pas juste. C'est ma vie. Tu as dיjא vיcu la tienne.
Papa Julio, I ask for your blessing.
Papב Julio, je demande ta bיnיdiction.
Tia Rosita? Oscar?
Tםa Rosita ? Oscar ?
Felipe? Tia Victoria?
Felipe ? Tםa Victoria ?
Don't make this hard, mr'jo. You go home my way or no way.
Ne te complique pas la vie, mijo. Tu rentreras selon mes conditions.
I will not let you go down the same path he did.
Je ne te laisserai pas suivre la mךme voie que lui.
The same path he did. He's family.
La mךme voie que lui. C'est ma famille.
-Listen to your Mama Imelda. -She's just looking out for you.
- ֹcoute mamב Imelda. - Elle ne veut que ton bien.
Be reasonable.
Sois raisonnable.
Con permiso, I need to visit the restroom. Be right back.
Con permiso, je dois aller aux toilettes. Je reviens.
Should we tell him there are no restrooms in the Land of the Dead?
On lui dit que le monde des ancךtres n'a pas de toilette ?
Vamonos.
Vבmonos.
We got a family looking for a living boy.
On a une famille qui cherche un garחon vivant.
If I want to be a musician, I need a musician's blessing.
C'est la bיnיdiction d'un musicien qu'il me faut.
We got to find my great-great-grandpa.
Trouvons arriטre-arriטre-grand-papa.
Hold it, muchacho.
Pas si vite, muchacho.
I found that living boy! Oh, whoa, excuse me. Excuse me, folks.
J'ai trouvי le garחon vivant ! Oh, pardon. Pardon, mes amis.
Excuse me.
Excusez-moi.
No, no. Dante!
Non, non. Dante !
Disturbing the peace. Fleeing an officer. Falsifying a unibrow.
Troubler la paix. Fuir un policier. Se dessiner un faux monosourcil.
-That's illegal? -Very illegal.
- C'est illיgal ? - Trטs.
You need to clean up your act, amigo.
Il faut vous reprendre en main, amigo.
Amigo? Oh, that's so nice to hear you say that because I have just had a...
Amigo ? C'est bon d'entendre חa, car je viens de passer
really hard Dla de Muertos and I could really use an amigo right now.
un Dםa de Muertos difficile et j'ai bien besoin d'un amigo.
And amigos, they help their amigos.
Les amigos aident leurs amigos.
You get me across that bridge tonight, and I'll make it worth your while.
Aidez-moi א traverser le pont ce soir et vous serez richement rיcompensי.
Oh! You like de la Cruz? He and I go way back.
Oh ! Vous aimez de la Cruz ? On se connaמt depuis toujours.
I'll get you backstage. You can meet him.
Vous pourrez le rencontrer dans les coulisses.
You just got to let me cross that bridge!
Il suffit de me laisser traverser !
I should lock you up for the rest of the holiday.
Je devrais vous enfermer pour le reste de la fךte.
But my shift's almost up and I want to visit my living family.
Mais mon quart achטve et je veux rendre visite א ma famille.
So I'm letting you off with a warning.
Je vous donne donc un simple avertissement.
-Can I at least get my costume back? -No.
- Puis-je ravoir mon costume ? - Non.
Some amigo.
Tu parles d'un amigo.
Hey! Hey! You really know de la Cruz?
Hי ! Tu connais rיellement de la Cruz ?
Who wants to-- Ay! You're alive!
Qui veut le... Ay ! Tu es vivant !
Sh! Yeah, I'm alive. And if I want to get back to the Land of the Living...
Chut ! Oui, et je ne retournerai pas dans le monde des vivants
I need de la Cruz's blessing.
sans la bיnיdiction de de la Cruz.
That's weirdly specific.
C'est drפlement prיcis.
He's my great—great—grandfather.
C'est mon arriטre-arriטre-grand-pטre.
He's your Gr-- What?
C'est ton... Quoi ?
Wait, wait, wait. Wait, wait.
Attends, attends. Attends.
Wait! Yes! You're going back to the Land of the Living!
Attends. Oui ! Tu retourneras dans le monde des vivants.
You know what? Maybe this isn't such a good--
Tu sais quoi ? C'est peut-ךtre une mauvaise...
No, no, nir”ro! Niﬁo, niﬁo, I can help you. You can help me.
Non, non, niסo ! Niסo, je peux t'aider. Tu peux m'aider.
We can help each other. But most importantly, you can help me.
On peut s'entraider. Mais par-dessus tout, tu peux m'aider.
-Miguel! -I'm Hector.
- Miguel ! - Je m'appelle Hיctor.
That's nice.
C'est chouette.
Espérame, chamaco!
Espיrame, chamaco !
Ay, he is going to get himself killed. I need my spirit guide... Pepita.
Ay, il va se faire tuer. J'ai besoin de mon guide spirituel... Pepita.
Who has that petal Miguel touched?
Qui a le pיtale que Miguel a touchי ?
Here. Nice alebrije.
Tiens. Gentil alebrije.
Ay, ay, hold still. Look up. A ver, a ver. Look up, up, up.
Ay, ay, ne bouge pas. Regarde en haut. A ver, a ver. Regarde vers le haut.
Aqui arriba, eso... Eh, la rayita.
Aqui arriba, eso... Eh, la rayita.
Okay. Hey! Ta-da!
Trטs bien. Hי ! Ta-dam !
Dead as a doorknob.
On ne peut plus mort.
So listen, Miguel, this place runs on memories.
ֹcoute, Miguel. Ici, tout dיpend des souvenirs.
When you're well remembered, people put up your photo and you get to...
Ceux qui se souviennent de nous exposent notre photo, et on peut
cross the bridge and visit the living on Dia de Muertos. Unless you're me.
traverser le pont pour visiter les vivants lors du Dםa de Muertos. Sauf moi.
You don't get to cross over?
Tu n'as pas le droit de traverser ?
No one's ever put up my picture. But you can change that!
Personne n'expose ma photo. Mais tu peux changer חa !
This is you?
C'est toi ?
Eh, muy guapo, eh?
Eh, muy guapo, eh ?
So, you get me to my great-great-grandpa. ..
Tu m'aideras א rejoindre mon arriטre-arriטre-grand-pטre
then I put up your photo when I get home?
et j'exposerai ta photo quand je serai rentrי chez moi ?
Such a smart boy! Yes! Great idea, yes! One hiccup.
Quel garחon futי ! Oui ! Excellente idיe. Il n'y a qu'un pיpin.
Dela Cruz is a tough guy to get to and I need to cross the bridge soon.
De la Cruz est difficile א rejoindre, et je dois vite traverser le pont.
Like, tonight. So, you got any other family here, you know?
Du genre ce soir. As-tu d'autres parents ici ?
Someone a bit more accessible?
Quelqu'un de plus accessible ?
Mm... Nope.
Hmm... Non.
Don't yank my chain, chamaco. You got to have some other family.
Ne me fais pas marcher, chamaco. Ce n'est srement pas le seul.
Only de la Cruz. Ifyou can't help me, I'll find him myself.
Il n'y a que de la Cruz. Je le trouverai seul si tu ne m'aides pas.
Oh! Okay. Okay, kid. Fine! Fine! I'll get you to your great-great-grandpa.
Trטs bien, petit ! Je trouverai ton arriטre-arriטre-grand-pטre.
It's not gonna be easy, you know? He's a busy man. What are you doing?
Mais ce ne sera pas facile. Il est occupי. Que fais-tu ?
I'm walking like a skeleton. Blending in.
Je marche comme un squelette pour passer inaperחu.
No. Skeletons don't walk like that.
Les squelettes ne marchent pas comme חa.
-It's how you walk. -No, Idon't! Stop it!
- Toi, oui. - Pas du tout ! Arrךte חa !
Whoa! Ernesto de la Cruz's Sunrise Spectacular? Qué padre!
Ouah ! L'Aurore spectaculaire d'Ernesto de la Cruz ? Quי padre !
Every year your great-great-grandpa puts on that dumb show...
Ton arriטre-arriטre-grand-pטre donne ce spectacle idiot chaque annיe
to mark the end of Dia de Muertos.
pour conclure le Dםa de Muertos.
And you can get us in!
Et tu peux nous faire entrer !
Hey, you said you have front row tickets!
Tu as dit que tu avais des places au premier rang !
That...was a lie. I apologize for that.
C'יtait... un mensonge. Excuse-moi.
Cool off, chamaco. Come on. I'll get you to him.
Du calme, chamaco. Viens. Je te conduis jusqu'א lui.
How?
Comment ?
Because I happen to know where he's rehearsing.
Il se trouve que je sais oש il rיpטte.
Remember me Don't let it make you cry
Ne m'oublie pas Tu ne dois pas pleurer
You better have my dress, Héctor.
J'espטre que tu as ma robe, Hיctor.
Hola, Ceci.
Hola, Ceci.
-Hola. -Ceci, I lost the dress.
- Hola. - Ceci, j'ai perdu la robe.
Ya Io sabia!
Ya lo sabםa !
I got to dress forty dancers by sunrise.
J'ai 40 danseurs א habiller d'ici l'aurore.
Thanks to you, I'm one Frida short of an opening number!
Par ta faute, il me manque une Frida pour le numיro d'ouverture.
Dante! We shouldn't be in here.
Dante ! On ne devrait pas ךtre lא.
No, no, Dante! Ven aca!
Non, non, Dante ! Ven acב !
-I just followed my-- -Oh! The mighty Xolo dog!
- J'ai simplement suivi mon... - Oh ! Le grand Xolo !
Guider of wandering spirits. And whose spirit have you guided to me?
Guide des esprits errants. Quel esprit as-tu conduit א moi ?
I don't think he's a spirit guide.
Je ne crois pas que c'est un guide spirituel.
The alebrijes of this world can take many forms.
Les alebrijes de ce monde prennent plusieurs formes.
They are as mysterious as they are powerful.
Ils sont aussi mystיrieux que puissants.
Or maybe he's just a dog. Come, I need your eyes.
Ou peut-ךtre que ce n'est qu'un chien. Viens, j'ai besoin de ton regard.
You are the audience. Darkness.
Tu es le public. L'obscuritי.
And from the darkness, a giant papaya.
Et dans l'obscuritי, une papaye gיante.
Dancers emerge from the papaya, and the dancers are all me.
Des danseurs יmergent de la papaye. Les danseurs sont tous moi.
And they go to drink from the milk of their mother, who is a cactus.
Ils vont boire le lait de leur mטre, qui est un cactus.
But who is also me. And her milk is not milk but tears.
Le cactus est יgalement moi. Son lait, c'est en fait des larmes.
Is it too obvious?
Est-ce trop יvident ?
I think it's just the right amount of obvious?
Je crois que c'est juste assez יvident.
It could use some music. Oh, what if you did like...
ַa manque de musique. Peut-ךtre que חa pourrait faire...
Oh! And then it could go...
Oh ! Et ensuite, חa donnerait...
And what if everything was on fire?
Et si tout יtait en feu ?
Yes! Fire! Everywhere!
Oui ! Du feu ! Partout !
Inspired! You have the spirit of an artist.
Quelle inspiration ! Tu as l'esprit d'un artiste.
The dancers exit. The music fades, the lights go out.
Les danseurs partent. La musique se tait, la lumiטre s'יteint.
And Ernesto de la Cruz rises to the stage!
Et Ernesto de la Cruz monte sur scטne !
Huh?
Hein ?
He does a couple of songs, the sun rises, everyone cheers--
Il chante un peu, le soleil se lטve, on l'acclame...
Excuse me, where's the real de la Cruz?
Pardon, oש est le vrai de la Cruz ?
Ernesto doesn't do rehearsals!
Ernesto ne rיpטte pas !
He's too busy hosting that fancy party at the top of his tower.
Il est trop occupי א donner une fךte au haut de sa tour.
Chamaco, you can't run off on me like that. Stop pestering the celebrities.
Chamaco, ne te sauve pas comme חa. Arrךte d'embךter les vedettes.
You said my great-great-grandpa would be here!
Mon arriטre-arriטre-grand-pטre devait ךtre ici !
He's halfway across town throwing some big party.
Il donne une fךte א l'autre bout de la ville.
That bum. Who doesn't show up to his own rehearsal?
Le vaurien. Qui rate sa propre rיpיtition ?
If you're such good friends, how come he didn't invite you?
Si vous ךtes de si bons amis, pourquoi ne t'a-t-il pas invitי ?
He's your great-great-grandpa,
Et toi ? C'est ton ancךtre. Pourquoi ne t'a-t-il pas invitי ?
Hey, Gustavo! You know anything about this party?
Gustavo ! Que sais-tu א propos de cette fךte ?
It's the hot ticket!
C'est l'יvיnement de la soirיe !
But if you're not on the guest list, you're never getting in, Chorizo.
Si tu n'es pas sur la liste d'invitיs, tu n'entreras jamais, Chorizo.
Hey! It's Chorizo! Choricito!
Hי ! C'est Chorizo ! Choricito !
Oh, this guy's famous! Go on, go on. Ask him how he died.
Il est cיlטbre ! Vas-y. Demande-lui comment il est mort.
I don't want to talk about it.
Je ne veux pas en parler.
He choked on some chorizo!
Il s'est יtouffי avec du chorizo !
I didn't choke, okay? I got food poisoning which is a big difference.
Je ne me suis pas יtouffי. C'יtait un empoisonnement alimentaire.
This is why I don't like musicians. Bunch of self-important jerks.
Je n'aime pas les musiciens. Ils se prennent pour d'autres.
-Hey! I'm a musician! -You are?
- Hי ! Je suis musicien, moi ! - Ah bon ?
If you really want to get to Ernesto, there is that music competition...
Si tu veux parler א Ernesto, il y a un concours de musique
at the Plaza de la Cruz. Winner gets to play at his party.
א la place de la Cruz. Le gagnant remporte une chance de jouer א sa fךte.
No, no. Chamaco, you're loco if you think--
Non, non. Chamaco, tu es loco si tu crois...
I need to get my great-great-grandfather's blessing!
Il faut qu'il m'accorde sa bיnיdiction !
You know where I can get a guitar?
Oש puis-je trouver une guitare ?
I know a guy.
Je connais un gars.
Have you found him, Pepita? Have you found our boy?
L'as-tu trouvי, Pepita ? As-tu trouvי notre garחon ?
-Pronated. -Miguel.
- Pronation. - Miguel.
Why the heck would you want to be a musician?
Pourquoi donc veux-tu devenir musicien ?
My great-great-grandpa was a musician!
Mon arriטre-arriטre-grand-pטre l'יtait !
Who spent his life performing like a monkey for complete strangers.
Il a passי sa vie א se donner en spectacle pour des inconnus.
No thank you. No! Guacalal
Non, merci. Non ! Guבcala !
What do you know? So, how far is this guitar anyway?
Qu'est-ce que tu y connais ? Elle est loin, cette guitare ?
We're almost there.
On y est presque.
Keep up, chamaco. Come on.
Allez, chamaco. Ne traמne pas.
-Cousin Héctor! -Hey! These guys! Hey, Tio!
- Cousin Hיctor ! - Hי ! Les gars ! Hי ! Tםo !
-5‘ Que onda? -These people are all your family?
- ¿ Quי onda ? - Ils sont tous de ta famille ?
In a way. We're all the ones with no photos or ofrendas.
Si on veut. On est ceux qui n'ont pas de photo ni d'ofrenda.
No family to go home to. Nearly forgotten, you know?
Pas de famille א visiter. On est presque oubliיs.
So, we all call each other cousin, or tio, or whatever.
On s'appelle tous cousin ou tםo, peu importe.
-Héctor! -Tia Chelo!
- Hיctor ! - Tםa Chelo !
Hey! Save some for me! Is Chicharrén around?
Hי ! Gardez-m'en ! Chicharrףn est-il lא ?
Eh, in the bungalow. Idon't know if he's in the mood for visitors.
Dans la maison. Je ne sais pas s'il a envie de recevoir de la visite.
Who doesn't like a visit from Cousin Hector?
Qui n'a pas envie de voir le cousin Hיctor ?
Buenas noches, Chicharrén!
Buenas noches, Chicharrףn !
I don't want to see your stupid face, Héctor.
Je ne veux pas voir ta drפle de tךte, Hיctor.
Come on. It's Dia de Muertos. I brought you a little offering.
Allons. C'est le Dםa de Muertos. Je t'ai apportי une offrande.
-Get out of here. -I would, Cheech.
- Dיgage. - Je voudrais bien, Cheech.
But the thing is, me and my friend, Miguel...
Sauf que mon ami Miguel et moi...
We really need to borrow your guitar.
On a besoin d'emprunter ta guitare.
-My guitar? -Yes.
- Ma guitare ? - Oui.
-My prized beloved guitar? -I promise we'll bring it right back.
- Ma guitare adorיe ? - Je promets de la rapporter.
Like the time you promised to bring back my van? Or my mini-fridge?
Comme la fois oש tu as rapportי mon camion ? Ou mon mini-frigo ?
-Ah, you see-— -Or my good napkins?
- Vois-tu... - Mes belles serviettes ?
My lasso? My femur?
Mon lasso ? Mon fיmur ?
-Well, no, not like those times. -Where is my femur? You——
- Non, pas comme חa. - Oש est mon fיmur ? Tu...
-You okay, amigo? -I'm fading, Héctor.
- ַa va, amigo ? - Je faiblis, Hיctor.
I can feel it. I couldn't even play that thing if I wanted to.
Je le sens. Je ne pourrais mךme pas en jouer si je le voulais.
You play me something.
Joue-moi quelque chose.
You want it, you got to earn it.
Si tu la veux, tu dois la mיriter.
Ay, only for you, amigo.
Ay, seulement pour toi, amigo.
An)’ requests?
Une demande spיciale ?
You know my favorite, Héctor.
Tu connais ma prיfיrיe, Hיctor.
Well, everyone knows Juanita
Tout le monde connaמt Juanita
Her eyes each a different color
Ses yeux de grenouille maquillיs
Her teeth stick out And her chin goes in
Son double menton Et ses dents dorיes
And her...
Ses...
Knuckles they drag on the ﬂoor
Gros citrons sont un peu tordus
-Those aren't the words. -There are children present.
- Ce n'est pas les bons mots. - Il y a des enfants ici.
Her hair is like a briar
Ses cheveux sont gras et fourchus
She stands in a bow—legged stance
Ses jambes poilues tremblent Quand elle danse
And if I weren't so ugly
Si moi je n'יtais pas si laid
She'd possibly give me a chance
Je pense qu'elle me laisserait Une chance
Brings back memories.
ַa me rappelle des souvenirs.
Gracias.
Gracias.
Wait. What happened?
Attends. Que s'est-il passי ?
He's been forgotten.
Il a יtי oubliי.
When there's no one left in the living world who remembers you...
Quand personne chez les vivants ne se souvient de nous,
you disappear from this world. We call it the final death.
on disparaמt de ce monde. On appelle חa la mort finale.
Where did he go?
Oש est-il allי ?
No one knows.
Personne ne le sait.
But I've met him. I could remember him when I go back!
Mais je l'ai rencontrי. Je pourrais me souvenir de lui א mon retour !
No, it doesn't work like that, chamaco.
ַa ne fonctionne pas ainsi, chamaco.
Our memories, they have to be passed down by those who knew us in life...
Notre souvenir doit ךtre transmis par ceux qui nous ont connus vivants,
in the stories they tell about us.
dans les histoires qu'ils racontent sur nous.
Hey, it happens to everyone eventually.
ַa finit par arriver א tout le monde.
Come on, de la Cruzcito, you've got a contest to win.
Viens, de la Cruzcito, tu as un concours א gagner.
You told me you hated musicians. You never said you were one.
Tu disais dיtester les musiciens. Tu m'as cachי que tu en יtais un.
How do you think I knew your great-great-grandpa?
Comment ai-je connu ton ancךtre, d'aprטs toi ?
We used to play music together. Taught him everything he knows.
On jouait de la musique ensemble. Je lui ai tout appris.
No manches! You played with Ernesto de la Cruz...
No manches ! Tu jouais avec Ernesto de la Cruz,
the greatest musician of all time?
le plus grand musicien de l'histoire ?
Ah, you're funny. Greatest eyebrows of all time maybe.
Tu es drפle. Les plus grands sourcils de l'histoire, peut-ךtre.
But his music? Eh, not so much.
Mais sa musique ? Bof.
You don't know what you're talking about.
Tu ne sais pas de quoi tu parles.
Llévelol T-shirts! Bobbleheadsl
Llיvelo ! Des chandails ! Des figurines !
Bien venidos a todos!
Bienvenidos a todos !
It's a battle of the bands, amigos.
C'est le combat des groupes, amigos.
The winner gets to play for the maestro himself, Ernesto de la Cruz...
Le gagnant jouera devant le maestro, Ernesto de la Cruz,
at his ﬁesta tonight!
א sa fiesta ce soir !
That's our ticket, muchacho.
C'est notre chance, muchacho.
Let the competition begin!
Que le concours commence !
So, what's the plan? What are you gonna play?
Alors, c'est quoi, ton plan ? Que joueras-tu ?
Definitely Remember Me.
Ne m'oublie pas, sans aucun doute.
-No! Not that one. No. -Come on. It's his most popular song!
- Non ! Pas חa. - C'est sa chanson la plus populaire !
It's too popular.
Trop populaire.
Remember me Though I have to travel far
Ne m'oublie pas Je vais devoir m'en aller
-Remember me... -Don't let it make you cry...
- Ne m'oublie pas... - Tu ne dois pas pleurer...
-What about Poco Loco? -Epa! Now that's a song!
- Pourquoi pas Poco Loco ? - Epa ! ַa, c'est une chanson.
De la Cruzcito? You're on standby. Los Chachalacos, you're up next.
De la Cruzcito ? Tiens-toi prךt. Los Chachalacos, א vous.
Los Chachalacos!
Los Chachalacos !
You always this nervous before a performance?
As-tu toujours autant le trac ?
I don't know. I've never performed before.
Je n'en sais rien. C'est mon premier spectacle.
What? You said you were a musician!
Quoi ? Tu as dit que tu יtais musicien !
lam! I mean, Iwill be.
Je le suis ! Enfin, je le serai.
-Ay! -Once I win.
- Ay ! - Quand j'aurai gagnי.
That's your plan? No. You have to win. Your life literally depends on...
C'est חa, ton plan ? Non. Tu dois gagner. Ta vie dיpend
you winning. And you've never done this before! I'll go up there.
de cette victoire. Et tu es dיbutant ! J'irai, moi.
-No! I need to do this. -Why?
- Non ! Ce doit ךtre moi. - Pourquoi ?
If I can't go out and play one song, how can I call myself a musician?
Si je ne peux pas jouer une chanson, comment me qualifier de musicien ?
What does that matter?
Qu'est-ce que חa change ?
Because I don'tjust want to get de la Cruz's blessing...
Je veux plus que la bיnיdiction de de la Cruz.
I need to prove that I'm worthy of it.
Je veux prouver que je la mיrite.
Oh, that's such a sweet sentiment at such a bad time!
C'est mignon, comme sentiment, mais ce n'est pas le moment !
Okay! Okay. You want to perform? Then you got to perform!
Trטs bien ! Tu veux chanter ? Tu vas chanter !
First, you have to loosen up. Shake off those nerves.
Il faut te dיtendre. Te calmer les nerfs.
Now give me your best grito.
Donne-moi ton meilleur grito.
-My best grito? -Come on, yell! Belt it out.
- Mon meilleur grito ? - Allez, crie ! ְ pleins poumons.
Ah, it feels good. Okay, now you.
ַa fait du bien. ְ ton tour.
Oh, come on, kid.
Allez, petit.
De la Cruzcito, you're on now!
De la Cruzcito, c'est א toi !
Miguel, look at me. Hey, look at me. You can do this.
Miguel, regarde-moi. Tu peux le faire.
Grab their attention and don't let it go.
Capte leur attention et ne la lגche pas.
Make them listen, chamaco. You've got this.
Fais-les t'יcouter, chamaco. Tu peux le faire.
De la Cruzcito!
De la Cruzcito !
What's he doing? Why isn't he playing?
Que fait-il ? Pourquoi ne joue-t-il pas ?
Bring back the singing dogs!
Ramenez les chiens chantants !
What color is the sky? A y mi amor, ay mi amor
De quelle couleur est l'azur ? Ay mi amor, ay mi amor
You tell me that it's red
Tu me dis rose crevette !
Where should I put my shoes? A y mi amor, ay mi amor
Qu'est-ce que je fais De mes chaussures ?
You say put them on your head
Tu dis : "Mets-les sur ta tךte"
You make me un poco loco Un poqui-ti-ti-to loco
Et tu me rends un poco loco Un poquititito loco
The way you keep me guessing I'm nodding and I'm yes-ing
Je suis un homme amoureux Qu'on ne prend plus au sיrieux
I'll count it as a blessing
Je peux m'estimer heureux
That I'm only un poco loco
D'ךtre seulement un poco loco
No! No! No!
Non ! Non ! Non !
-Not bad for a dead guy! -Not so bad yourself, gordito! Eso!
- Pas mal pour un mort ! - Pas mal toi-mךme, gordito ! Eso !
He's close! Find him!
Il est tout prטs ! Trouvez-le !
The loco that you make me It is just un poco crazy
Le loco que je deviens Est si fou qu'il ne comprend rien
The sense that you're not making
Toutes ces phrases que tu rיpטtes
The liberties you're taking
Et toutes ces soirיes de fךte
Leaves my cabeza shaking You're just un poco loco
Qui me font tourner la tךte Oui tu es un poco loco
-We're looking for a living kid. -About twelve?
- On cherche un garחon vivant. - De 12 ans ?
Have you seen a living boy?
Avez-vous vu un garחon vivant ?
Un poqui-ti-ti-ti-ti-ti-ti-ti-ti-ti-to loco
Un poqui-tititititititititititittititito Loco
Hey! You did good! I'm proud of you. Eso!
Hי ! Tu as rיussi ! Je suis fier de toi ! Eso !
Otra! Otra! Otra!
Otra ! Otra ! Otra !
-Hey! Where are you going? -We got to get out of here!
- Hי ! Oש vas-tu ? - Il faut partir !
What? Are you crazy? We're about to win this thing.
Quoi ? Es-tu fou ? On va gagner ce concours.
Damas y cabal/eros, I have an emergency announcement.
Damas y caballeros, j'ai un message urgent.
Please be on the lookout for a living boy. Answers to the name of Miguel.
On recherche un garחon vivant qui rיpond au nom de Miguel.
Earlier tonight he ran away from his family.
Il s'est enfui de sa famille plus tפt ce soir.
Theyjust want to send him back to the Land of the Living.
Ils veulent le renvoyer dans le monde des vivants.
Wait, wait. You said de la Cruz was your only family.
Attends. Tu as dit que de la Cruz יtait ton seul parent.
The only person who could send you home.
Le seul qui pouvait te renvoyer chez toi.
You could have taken my photo back this whole time?
Tu aurais dיjא pu rapporter ma photo ?
But they hate music! I need a musician's blessing.
Ils dיtestent la musique ! Il faut la bיnיdiction d'un musicien.
-You lied to me! -You're one to talk.
- Tu m'as menti. - Tu peux bien parler.
Look at me. I'm being forgotten, Miguel.
Regarde-moi. Je sombre dans l'oubli, Miguel.
I don't even know if I'm gonna last the night.
J'ignore si je passerai la nuit.
I'm not gonna miss my one chance to cross that bridge because...
Je ne raterai pas ma chance de franchir le pont
you want to live out some stupid musical fantasy.
parce que tu as voulu vivre un fantasme musical idiot.
-It's not stupid! -I'm taking you to your family.
- Il n'est pas idiot ! - Je te ramטne א ta famille.
-Let go of me! -You'll thank me later.
- Lגche-moi ! - Tu m'en remercieras.
You don't want to help me. You only care about yourself!
Tu ne veux pas m'aider. Tu ne penses qu'א toi !
Keep your dumb photo. Stay away from me!
Garde ta stupide photo. Tiens-toi loin de moi !
No!
Non !
Hey, chamaco! Where did you go?
Hי, chamaco ! Oש es-tu passי ?
Chamaco! I'm sorry! Come back!
Chamaco ! Excuse-moi ! Reviens !
Dante, callate! No! Dante, stop it.
Dante, cבllate ! Non ! Dante, arrךte.
He can't help me. Dante! Stop!
Il ne peut pas m'aider.
Stop it! Leave me alone!
Arrךte חa ! Laisse-moi tranquille !
You're not a spirit guide. You're just a dumb dog! Now get out of here!
Tu n'es pas un guide spirituel, mais un chien idiot ! Dיgage !
-It's him! —|t's that living boy!
- C'est lui ! - C'est le garחon vivant !
-I heard about him. Look! -He's alive!
- J'en ai entendu parler. - Il est vivant !
This nonsense ends now, Miguel!
Ce cirque se termine maintenant, Miguel !
I am giving you my blessing and you are going home.
Je te donne ma bיnיdiction, et tu rentres chez toi.
I don't want your blessing!
Je ne veux pas ta bיnיdiction !
Miguel, stop!
Miguel, arrךte !
Come back! Miguel!
Reviens ! Miguel !
I am trying to save your life!
J'essaie de te sauver la vie !
-You're ruining my life! -What?
- Tu gגches ma vie ! - Quoi ?
Music's the only thing that makes me happy. And you want to take it away.
Seule la musique me rend heureux, et tu veux me l'enlever.
You'll never understand.
Tu ne comprendras jamais.
Y aunque la vida me cueste, Llorona
Y aunque la vida me cueste, Llorona
No dejaré de quererte...
No dejarי de quererte...
I thought you hated music.
Je croyais que tu dיtestais la musique.
I loved it! I remember that feeling...
J'adorais חa ! Je me rappelle ce sentiment,
when my husband would play, and I would sing and nothing else mattered.
quand mon mari jouait, que je chantais et que rien d'autre n'importait.
But when we had Coco, suddenly there was something in my life that...
Mais quand Coco est nיe, tout d'un coup, j'avais quelque chose
mattered more than music. I wanted to put down roots.
qui comptait plus que la musique. J'יtais prךte א m'יtablir.
He wanted to play for the world.
Il voulait jouer pour le monde entier.
We each made a sacrifice to get what we wanted.
On a tous deux fait un sacrifice pour obtenir ce qu'on voulait.
Now you must make a choice.
ְ ton tour de faire un choix.
But I don't want to pick sides!
Mais je ne veux pas choisir un camp !
Why can't you be on my side? That's what family's supposed to do.
Pourquoi ne m'appuies-tu pas ? C'est ce que devrait faire une famille.
Support you. But you never will.
Offrir son soutien. Mais tu ne le feras jamais.
-Have a good time. -Oh, how exciting!
- Amusez-vous bien. - C'est emballant !
Oh, El Santo. I'm a big fan! You mind if I...
El Santo, je suis un grand admirateur ! Me permettez-vous...
Gracias, Senor.
Gracias, seסor.
-Invitation? -It's okay.
- Votre invitation ? - Pas besoin.
I'm Ernesto's great-great-grandson.
Je suis l'arriטre-arriטre-petit-fils d'Ernesto.
-Discu/pen, seﬁores... -Hey, guys! It's poco loco!
- Disculpen, seסores... - Les amis ! C'est poco loco !
-You were on fire tonight! -You too!
- Tu יtais tout feu tout flammes. - Vous aussi !
Hey, musician to musician... I need a favor.
Dites, entre musiciens... J'ai besoin d'un service.
The competition winners. Congratulations, chicos.
Les gagnants du concours. Fיlicitations, chicos.
Thanks, guys!
Merci, les amis !
-Hey! Enjoy the party, little musico! -Gracias!
- Profite de la fךte, petit mתsico ! - Gracias !
Oh!
Oh !
Look! It's Ernesto!
Regarde ! C'est Ernesto !
De la Cruz!
De la Cruz !
Seﬁor de la Cruz!
Seסor de la Cruz !
Pardon me! Senor de la Cruz! Senor de la--
Pardon ! Seסor de la Cruz ! Seסor de la...
When you see your moment, you mustn't let it pass you by.
Quand vient le moment, il ne faut pas le laisser passer.
You must seize it.
Il faut le saisir.
This one has a wise spirit.
Son גme est sage.
We're almost there, Dante.
On y est presque, Dante.
Senor de la Cruz! Senor de la--
Seסor de la Cruz ! Seסor de la...
But what can we do? It is hopeless...
Que peut-on faire ? C'est sans espoir...
-You must have faith, sister. -But Padre, he will never listen.
- Ayez la foi, ma sur. - Mais padre, il n'יcoute jamais.
He will listen... to music.
Il יcoutera la musique.
Buenas tardes, buenas noches Senoritas y senores
Buenas tardes, buenas noches Seסoritas y seסores
To be here with you tonight Brings me joy! Qué alegrla
tre parmi vous ce soir Que de joie, quי alegrםa
For this music is my language And the world es mi familia
Car la musique est mon langage Et le monde es mi familia
For this music is my lang--
Car la musique est mon lang...
Are you all right, nino?
Tout va bien, niסo ?
It's you! You are that boy! The one who came from the Land of the Living.
C'est toi ! Le garחon venu du monde des vivants !
You...know about me?
Vous... ךtes au courant ?
You are all anyone has been talking about. Why have you come here?
Tout le monde ne parle que de toi. Pourquoi es-tu venu ici ?
I'm Miguel. Your great-great-grandson.
Je suis Miguel, votre arriטre-arriטre-petit-fils.
I... have a great-great-grandson?
J'ai... un arriטre-arriטre-petit-fils ?
I need your blessing so I can go back home and be a musician.
J'ai besoin de votre bיnיdiction pour rentrer et devenir musicien.
Just like you. The rest of our family, they wouldn't listen.
Comme vous. Le reste de la famille ne veut rien entendre.
But I hoped you would.
Mais j'espיrais que vous comprendriez.
My boy, with a talent like yours, how could I not listen?
Petit, avec un talent comme le tien, comment ne pas t'יcouter ?
I have a great-great-grandson!
J'ai un arriטre-arriטre-petit-fils !
-Look! It's Frida! -Yes, it is I. Frida Kahlo.
- Regardez ! C'est Frida ! - Oui, c'est moi. Frida Kahlo.
-It is an honor, Senora. -Gracias.
- C'est un honneur, seסora. - Gracias.
Hey, Negrete! Infantel Have you met my great-great-grandson?
Negrete ! Infante ! Connaissez-vous mon arriטre-arriטre-petit-fils ?
My great-great-grandson.
Mon arriטre-arriטre-petit-fils.
He's alive! And a musician to boot!
Il est vivant ! Et c'est un musicien !
Dimple. No dimple. Dimple. No dimple.
Fossette. Pas de fossette.
No dimple!
Pas de fossette !
To our friendship.
ְ notre amitiי.
Poison!
Du poison !
You know, I did all my own stunts.
Je faisais toutes mes cascades, tu sais.
Though I have to say goodbye Remember me...
Je vais devoir m'en aller Ne m'oublie pas...
All of this came from my amazing fans in the Land of the Living.
Tout חa vient de mes admirateurs dans le monde des vivants.
They leave me more offerings than I know what to do with!
Ils me laissent tant d'offrandes que je ne sais qu'en faire !
Hey, what's wrong? Is it too much? You look overwhelmed.
Qu'est-ce qui ne va pas ? C'est trop ? Tu sembles dיpassי par tout חa.
-No! It's all great! -But?
- Non ! C'est super ! - Mais ?
It's just-- I have been looking up to you my whole life.
Je t'ai admirי toute ma vie.
You're the guy who actually did it!
Tu es celui qui a connu un יnorme succטs !
But did you ever regret it? Choosing music over everything else?
Mais as-tu dיjא regrettי d'avoir tout laissי pour la musique ?
It was hard. Saying goodbye to my hometown. Heading off on my own...
C'יtait dur de dire adieu א mon village. De partir seul...
Leaving your family?
D'abandonner ta famille ?
One cannot deny who one is meant to be.
Nul ne peut nier son destin.
And you, my great-great-grandson, are meant to be a musician!
Et toi, mon arriטre-arriטre-petit-fils, tu es destinי א devenir musicien !
You and I, we are artists, Miguel. We cannot belong to one family.
On est des artistes, toi et moi, Miguel. Une famille ne nous suffit pas.
The world is our family.
Le monde entier est notre famille.
The fireworks have begun!
Les feux d'artifice ont commencי !
Soon the party will move across town for my Sunrise Spectacular.
La fךte se dיplacera א l'autre bout de la ville pour l'Aurore spectaculaire.
Miguel, you must come to the show! You will be my guest of honor!
Miguel, tu dois venir au spectacle ! Tu seras mon invitי d'honneur !
-You mean it? -Of course, my boy.
- Tu es sיrieux ? - Mais oui, mon garחon.
I can't. I have to get home before sunrise.
Je ne peux pas. Je dois rentrer chez moi avant l'aurore.
Oh! I really do need to get you home.
Oh ! Je ne dois pas traמner, alors.
It has been an honor. I am sorry to see you go, Miguel.
Ce fut un honneur. Je regrette que tu doives partir, Miguel.
I hope you die very soon.
J'espטre que tu mourras bientפt.
You know what I mean.
Tu sais ce que je veux dire.
-Miguel, I give you my b|ess-- -We had a deal, chamaco.
- Miguel, je t'accorde ma bיnי... - On avait une entente, chamaco.
Who are you? What is the meaning of this?
Qui es-tu ? Qu'est-ce qui se passe ?
Frida! I thought you couldn't make it.
Frida ! Je croyais que tu ne pouvais pas venir.
You said you'd take back my photo. You promised, Miguel.
Tu devais rapporter ma photo. Tu l'as promis, Miguel.
You know this man?
Tu connais cet homme ?
Ijust met him tonight. He told me he knew you.
Je l'ai rencontrי ce soir. Il m'a dit qu'il te connaissait.
Héctor?
Hיctor ?
Please, Miguel. Put my photo up.
Je t'en prie, Miguel. Expose ma photo.
Those were my songs you took. My songs that made you famous.
Tu m'as volי mes chansons. C'est elles qui t'ont rendu cיlטbre.
What?
Quoi ?
If I'm being forgotten, it's because you never told anyone that I wrote them!
On m'oublie, car tu n'as dit א personne que je les avais composיes !
That's crazy! De la Cruz wrote all his own songs.
N'importe quoi ! De la Cruz composait ses propres chansons.
You want to tell him or should I?
Tu lui dis ou c'est א moi de le faire ?
Héctor, I never meant to take credit. We made a great team, but you died...
Hיctor, je ne voulais pas m'attribuer le mיrite. On formait une belle יquipe.
and I only sang your songs because I wanted to keep a part of you alive.
Aprטs ta mort, j'ai chantי tes chansons pour qu'une partie de toi vive encore.
How generous!
Quelle gיnיrositי !
You really did play together.
C'est donc vrai. Vous jouiez ensemble.
I don't want to fight about it. Ijust want you to make it right.
Je ne veux pas qu'on se dispute, seulement que tu te rachטtes.
Miguel can put my photo up, and I can cross over the bridge.
Miguel pourra exposer ma photo, et je pourrai traverser le pont.
Heaven and Earth’? Like in the movie?
Ciel et terre ? Comme dans le film ?
In the de la Cruz movie, El Camino a Casa.
Dans le film de de la Cruz, El Camino a Casa.
I would move Heaven and Earth for you, mi amigo.
Je remuerais ciel et terre pour toi, mi amigo.
—Salud! -Poison!
- Salud ! - Du poison !
That night, Ernesto. The night I left...
Cette nuit-lא, Ernesto. La nuit de mon dיpart...
We'd been performing on the road for months. I got homesick...
On יtait en tournיe depuis des mois. La maison me manquait,
and I packed up my songs.
et j'ai empaquetי mes chansons.
You want to give up now when we're this close to reaching our dream?
Tu veux abandonner alors que le rךve est א notre portיe ?
You walked me to the train station. But I felt a pain in my stomach.
Tu m'as accompagnי א la gare. J'ai ressenti une douleur א l'estomac.
I thought it must have been something I ate.
J'ai attribuי חa א une chose que j'avais mangיe.
You poisoned me.
Tu m'as empoisonnי.
You're confusing movies with reality, Héctor.
Tu confonds le cinיma et la rיalitי, Hיctor.
All this time, I thought it was just bad luck.
Tout ce temps, je croyais avoir יtי victime de malchance.
I never thought that you might have-- That you...
Je n'aurais jamais pensי que tu aurais pu... Que toi...
-How could you? -Héctor!
- Comment as-tu pu ? - Hיctor !
Security! Security!
Sיcuritי ! Sיcuritי !
You took everything away from me! You rat!
Tu m'as tout enlevי ! Espטce de rat !
Have him taken care of. He's not well.
Qu'on s'occupe de lui. Il ne va pas bien.
I apologize. Where were we?
Excuse-moi. Oש en יtions-nous ?
You were going to give me your blessing.
Tu allais me donner ta bיnיdiction.
Yes. Sr’.
Oui. Sם.
You don't think that. Do you?
Tu ne crois pas חa, n'est-ce pas ?
Papa Ernesto, my blessing?
Papב Ernesto, ma bיnיdiction ?
Security? Take care of Miguel. He'll be extending his stay.
Sיcuritי ? Occupez-vous de Miguel. Il va prolonger son sיjour.
What? But I'm your family!
Quoi ? Mais je suis de ta famille !
Success doesn't come for free, Miguel.
Le succטs exige des sacrifices, Miguel.
I know you understand.
Je sais que tu comprends חa.
No! No!
Non ! Non !
-Héctor? -Kid?
- Hיctor ? - Petit ?
They told me not to be like de la Cruz, but I didn't listen.
Elle m'a dit de ne pas ךtre comme de la Cruz, mais je l'ai ignorיe.
I told them I didn't care if they remembered me.
Je lui ai dit que je me fichais qu'elle se souvienne de moi.
I didn't care if I was on their stupid ofrenda.
Que je me fichais d'ךtre sur son ofrenda idiote.
-Who? -My daughter.
- Qui ? - Ma fille.
She's the reason you wanted to cross the bridge.
C'est pour elle que tu voulais traverser le pont.
I just wanted to see her again. I never should have left Santa Cecilia.
Je voulais seulement la revoir. Je n'aurais pas d quitter Santa Cecilia.
I wish I could apologize.
J'aimerais pouvoir m'excuser.
I wish I could tell her that her papa was trying to come home.
J'aimerais pouvoir lui dire que son papב voulait rentrer.
That he loved her so much.
Qu'il l'aimait plus que tout.
Coco?
Coco ?
Where did you get this?
Oש as-tu trouvי חa ?
Is that you?
Et lא, c'est toi ?
We're... family?
On est de la mךme famille ?
I always hoped I'd see her again. That she'd miss me.
J'ai toujours espיrי que je la reverrais. Que je lui manquerais.
Maybe put up my photo. But it never happened.
Qu'elle exposerait ma photo. Ce n'est jamais arrivי.
You know the worst part?
Sais-tu ce qui est pire que tout ?
I thought at least one day I'd see her here. Give her the biggest hug.
au moins, un jour, je la verrais ici. Je lui donnerais un יnorme cגlin.
But she's the last person who remembers me.
Mais elle est la seule personne א se souvenir de moi.
You disappear... from this one. You'll never get to see her.
Tu disparaמtras de celui-ci. Tu ne pourras plus la revoir.
Ever again.
Plus jamais.
You know, I wrote her a song once.
Je lui avais composי une chanson.
We used to sing it every night at the same time.
On la chantait chaque soir א la mךme heure.
No matter how far apart we were.
Peu importe la distance qui nous sיparait.
What I wouldn't give to sing it to her one... last... time.
Je donnerais tout pour la lui chanter une derniטre fois.
Remember me
Ne m'oublie pas
Don't let it make you cry
Tu ne dois pas pleurer
For even if I'm far away I hold you in my heart
Mךme quand je suis trטs loin de toi Tu restes dans mon cur
Though I have to travel far Remember me
C'est א regret que je pars Ne m'oublie pas
Each time you hear a sad guitar
Quand tu entendras une guitare
Know that I'm with you The only way that I can be
Tu ne me vois pas Pourtant je suis tout prטs de toi
Until you're in my arms again
Quand je chante Tu es dans mes bras
Remember me
Ne m'oublie pas
He stole your guitar. He stole your songs.
Il t'a volי ta guitare. Il t'a volי tes chansons.
You should be the one the world remembers, not de la Cruz!
C'est toi que le monde devrait se rappeler, pas de la Cruz !
I didn't write Remember Me for the world. I wrote it for Coco.
Je n'ai pas composי Ne m'oublie pas pour le monde, mais pour Coco.
I'm a pretty sorry excuse for a great-great-grandpa.
Je suis plutפt minable comme arriטre-arriטre-grand-pטre.
You're a total upgrade. My whole life, there's been something...
Tu es bien mieux que lui. Toute ma vie, il y a eu quelque chose
that made me different. And I never knew where it came from.
qui me rendait diffיrent. Je ne savais pas d'oש חa venait.
Dante?
Dante ?
Dante!
Dante !
It's Dante!
C'est Dante !
You look good.
Tu as l'air en forme.
Dante! You knew he was my Papa Héctor the whole time!
Dante ! Tu savais que c'יtait mon papב Hיctor depuis le dיbut !
You are a real spirit guide.
Tu es un vrai guide spirituel.
Who's the good spirit guide? You are!
C'est qui, le gentil guide spirituel ? C'est toi !
Dante!
Dante !
There they are!
Les voilא !
Miguel! Miguelito! Look, it's Miguel! He's all right.
Miguel ! Miguelito ! Regardez, c'est Miguel ! Il va bien.
Mr'jo, I was so worried! Thank goodness we found you in time.
Mijo, j'יtais si inquiטte ! Dieu merci, on t'a trouvי א temps.
And you... How many times must I turn you away?
Et toi... Combien de fois faut-il que je te renvoie ?
Imelda.
Imelda.
I want nothing to do with you! Not in life, not in death!
Je ne veux pas avoir affaire א toi ! Ni dans la vie, ni dans la mort !
I spent decades protecting my family from your mistakes.
J'ai passי des dיcennies א protיger ma famille de tes erreurs.
He spends five minutes with you and I have to fish him out of a sinkhole!
Il passe cinq minutes avec toi, et je dois le rescaper d'un gouffre !
I wasn't in there because of Héctor.
Je n'יtais pas lא א cause d'Hיctor.
He was in there because of me. He was just trying to get me home!
Il יtait lא א cause de moi. Il essayait de me renvoyer chez moi !
I didn't want to listen, but he was right.
Je ne voulais pas יcouter, mais il avait raison.
Nothing's more important than family.
Rien n'est plus important que la famille.
I'm ready to accept your blessing.
Je suis prךt א accepter ta bיnיdiction.
And your conditions. But first, I need to find de la Cruz.
Et tes conditions. Mais je dois d'abord trouver de la Cruz
To get Héctor's photo.
pour rיcupיrer la photo d'Hיctor.
-What? -So he can see Coco again.
- Quoi ? - Afin qu'il revoie Coco.
Héctor should be on our ofrenda. He's part of our family.
Hיctor devrait ךtre sur notre ofrenda. Il fait partie de la famille.
He left this family!
Il a abandonnי notre famille !
He tried to go home to you and Coco. But de la Cruz murdered him!
Il voulait rentrer vous retrouver, Coco et toi. De la Cruz l'a assassinי !
-It's true, Imelda. -And so what if it's true?
- C'est vrai, Imelda. - Et alors ?
You leave me alone with a child to raise...
Tu m'as laissיe seule avec une enfant א יlever
and I'm just supposed to forgive you?
et je suis censיe te pardonner ?
Imelda, I--
Imelda, je...
Héctor!
Hיctor !
I'm running out of time. It's Coco.
Je vais manquer de temps. C'est Coco.
She's forgetting you.
Elle t'oublie.
You don't have to forgive him. But we shouldn't forget him.
Tu n'es pas obligיe de le pardonner, mais on ne doit pas l'oublier.
I wanted to forget you.
J'ai voulu t'oublier.
I wanted Coco to forget you too, but...
Je voulais que Coco t'oublie aussi, mais...
This is my fault. Not yours.
C'est ma faute. Pas la tienne.
I'm sorry, Imelda.
Je suis navrי, Imelda.
Miguel, if we help you get his photo, you will return home?
Miguel, si on t'aide א rיcupיrer sa photo, rentreras-tu chez toi ?
No more music?
Ce sera fini, la musique ?
Family comes first.
La famille passe avant tout.
I can't forgive you.
Je ne peux pas te pardonner.
But I will help you.
Mais je t'aiderai.
So, how do we get to de la Cruz?
Comment se rendre jusqu'א de la Cruz ?
I might know a way.
Je crois connaמtre un moyen.
—Good luck, muchacho. -Gracias, Frida.
- Bonne chance, muchacho. - Gracias, Frida.
-Here, let me help you with-- -Don't touch me!
- Laisse-moi t'aider avec... - Pas touche !
Got your petals?
Avez-vous vos pיtales ?
Now, we just have to find de la Cruz.
Il ne reste qu'א trouver de la Cruz.
Yes?
Oui ?
Don't I know you?
On se connaמt, non ?
That's for murdering the love of my life!
ַa, c'est pour avoir assassinי l'amour de ma vie !
-I'm the love of your life? -I don't know. I'm still angry at you.
- Je suis l'amour de ta vie ? - Je n'en sais rien. Je t'en veux.
And that's for trying to murder my grandson.
Et חa, c'est pour avoir essayי d'assassiner mon petit-fils.
-Grandson? -She's talking about me!
- Petit-fils ? - Elle parle de moi !
You! Wait. You're related to Héctor?
Toi ! Attends. Tu fais partie de la famille d'Hיctor ?
The photo!
La photo !
After him!
Attrapons-le !
Security! Ayudenme!
Sיcuritי ! Ayתdenme !
-You said love of your life. -I don't know what I said.
- Tu as parlי d'amour de ta vie. - Je ne sais pas ce que j'ai dit.
That's what I heard.
C'est ce que j'ai entendu.
Places, Senor. You're on in thirty seconds.
En place, seסor. ְ vous dans 30 secondes.
Ay! Miguel! I have it!
Ay ! Miguel ! Je l'ai !
Hurry! Come on!
Vite ! Allez !
Ladies and gentlemen...
Mesdames et messieurs,
Get her off the stage.
Faites-lui quitter la scטne.
Sing! Sing!
Chante ! Chante !
Llorona de azul celeste
Llorona de azul celeste
Y aunque la vida me cueste, Llorona
Y aunque la vida me cueste, Llorona
No dejaré de quererte
No dejarי de quererte
A ver site divisaba
A ver si te divisaba
Como el pino era tierno, Llorona
Como el pino era tierno, Llorona
AI verme Ilorar, lloraba
Al verme llorar, lloraba
Ay de mi Llorona, Llorona Llorona de azul celeste
Ay de mם Llorona, Llorona Llorona de azul celeste
Y aunque la vida me cueste, Llorona
Y aunque la vida me cueste, Llorona
No dejaré de quererte
No dejarי de quererte
No dejaré de quererte
No dejarי de quererte
A y, ay, 3}’
Ay, ay, ay
You still got it.
Tu n'as rien perdu de ton talent.
You're going home.
Tu rentres chez toi.
Stay back! Stay back! All of you, stay back. Not one more step.
Arriטre ! Arriטre ! Que personne ne fasse un pas !
Dante!
Dante !
Ernesto, stop! Leave the boy alone.
Ernesto, arrךte ! Laisse le garחon tranquille.
I've worked too hard, Héctor. Too hard to let him destroy everything.
Hיctor, j'ai travaillי trop fort pour le laisser tout dיtruire.
He's a living child, Ernesto.
C'est un enfant vivant, Ernesto.
He's a threat!
C'est une menace !
You think I'd let him go back to the Land of the Living with your photo?
Tu crois que je le laisserais rentrer chez les vivants avec ta photo ?
To keep your memory alive? No.
Pour prיserver ton souvenir ? Non.
-You're a coward! -I am Ernesto de la Cruz.
- Lגche ! - Je suis Ernesto de la Cruz.
Héctor's the real musician.
C'est Hיctor, le vrai musicien.
You're just the guy who murdered him and stole his songs!
Vous ךtes celui qui l'a tuי pour voler ses chansons !
Murdered?
Tuי ?
Whatever it takes.
Cote que cote.
Miguel!
Miguel !
Apologies, old friend. But the show must go on.
Excuse-moi, mon vieil ami, mais le spectacle doit continuer.
Please, please, mi familia.
Je vous en prie, mi familia.
Murderer!
Assassin !
Orchestra. A-one, a-two, a-one--
Musique ! Un, deux, tr...
Remember me Though I have to s-- Hey!
Ne m'oublie pas Je vais devoir... Hי !
Nice kitty.
Gentil chaton.
No! No!
Non ! Non !
What did I miss?
Qu'est-ce que j'ai ratי ?
Good boy, Dante!
Bon chien, Dante !
Miguel!
Miguel !
Héctor! The photo... I lost it!
Hיctor ! La photo... Je l'ai perdue !
It's okay, mr'jo. It's 0--
Ce n'est pas grave, mijo. Ce n'est pas...
Héctor! Héctor?
Hיctor ! Hיctor ?
Coco.
Coco.
No! We can still find the photo.
Non ! On peut encore trouver la photo.
Miguel, it's almost sunrise.
Miguel, c'est presque l'aurore.
No, no. I can't leave you.
Non. Je ne peux pas te laisser.
I promised I'd put your photo up. I promised you'd see Coco.
J'ai promis d'exposer ta photo. J'ai promis que tu verrais Coco.
We're both out of time, mr'jo.
On va manquer de temps tous les deux, mijo.
Oh no! No! She can't forget you!
Non ! Elle ne peut pas t'oublier !
Ijust wanted her to know that I loved her.
Je voulais seulement qu'elle sache que je l'aime.
-Héctor! -You have our blessing, Miguel.
- Hיctor ! - Tu as notre bיnיdiction, Miguel.
No conditions.
Sans condition.
No! Papa Héctor, please!
Non ! Papב Hיctor, je t'en prie !
No!
Non !
—Go home. -I promise I won't let Coco forget you!
- Rentre chez toi. - Coco ne t'oubliera pas, c'est promis !
There he is!
Le voilא !
Miguel! Stop!
Miguel ! Arrךte !
-Where have you been? -I need to see Mama Coco, please.
- Oש יtais-tu ? - Je dois voir mamב Coco.
What are you doing with that-- Give it to me!
Que fais-tu avec ce... Donne-moi חa !
Miguel, stop! Miguel! Miguel!
Miguel, arrךte ! Miguel !
Mama Coco? Can you hear me? It's Miguel.
Mamב Coco ? M'entends-tu ? C'est Miguel.
I saw your papa. Remember? Papa?
J'ai vu ton papב. Tu te rappelles ? Papב ?
Please! If you forget him, he'll be gone. Forever.
Je t'en prie ! Si tu l'oublies, il disparaמtra א jamais.
Miguel, open this door!
Miguel, ouvre cette porte !
See? There he is! Papa! Remember? Papa?
Tu vois ? Le voilא ! Papב ! Tu te rappelles ? Papב ?
-Miguel! -Mama Coco, please! Don't forget him.
- Miguel ! - Mamב Coco, je t'en prie ! Rappelle-toi.
What are you doing to that poor woman? It's okay, Mamita. It's okay.
Que fais-tu א cette pauvre femme ? ַa va, mamita. ַa va.
I thought I'd lost you, Miguel.
Je croyais t'avoir perdu, Miguel.
I'm sorry, Papa.
Je te demande pardon, papב.
We're all together now. That's what matters.
On est tous ensemble א prיsent. C'est tout ce qui compte.
Not all of us.
Non, pas tous ensemble.
It's okay, Mamita. Miguel, you apologize to your Mama Coco.
ַa va, mamita. Miguel, excuse-toi א mamב Coco.
Mama Coco?
Mamב Coco ?
Well? Apologize!
Eh bien ? Excuse-toi !
Your papa, he wanted you to have this.
Ton papב voulait te donner חa.
Mama, wait!
Mamב, attends !
Remember me
Ne m'oublie pas
Though I have to say goodbye
Je vais devoir m'en aller
Don't let it make you cry
Tu ne dois pas pleurer
For even if I'm far away
Mךme si je suis trטs loin de toi
I hold you in my heart I sing a secret song to you
Tu restes dans mon cur Je chante en secret chaque soir
Each night we are apart
Pour que tu n'aies plus peur
Remember me
Ne m'oublie pas
Though I have to travel far
C'est א regret que je pars
Until you're in my arms again
Quand je chante Tu es dans mes bras
Remember me
Ne m'oublie pas
Elena? What's wrong, mr'ja?
Elena ? Qu'est-ce qui ne va pas, mija ?
Nothing, Mama. Nothing at all.
Rien, mamב. Rien du tout.
My papa used to sing me that song.
Mon papב me chantait cette chanson.
He loved you, Mama Coco.
Il t'aimait, mamב Coco.
Your papa loved you so much.
Ton papב t'aimait plus fort que tout.
I kept his letters.
J'ai gardי ses lettres.
Poems he wrote me. And...
Des poטmes qu'il m'יcrivait. Et...
Papa was a musician.
Papב יtait musicien.
When I was a little girl...
Quand j'יtais petite,
he and Mama would sing such beautiful songs.
mamב et lui chantaient de superbes chansons.
And right over here, one of Santa Cecilia's greatest treasures.
Et par ici, un des plus grands trיsors de Santa Cecilia,
The home of the esteemed song writer, Héctor Rivera.
la rיsidence du parolier de renom Hיctor Rivera.
The letters Héctor wrote home for his daughter, Coco, contain the lyrics...
Les lettres qu'Hיctor יcrivait א sa fille Coco contiennent les paroles
for all of your favorite songs. Not just Remember Me.
de toutes vos chansons prיfיrיes, pas seulement Ne m'oublie pas.
And that man is your Papa Julio.
Cet homme, c'est ton papב Julio.
And there's Tr’a Rosita and your Tia Victoria.
Et lא, c'est tםa Rosita et tםa Victoria.
And those two are Oscar and Felipe.
Ces deux-lא, c'est Oscar et Felipe.
These aren'tjust old pictures, they're our family...
C'est plus que des vieilles photos : c'est notre famille,
and they're counting on us to remember them.
et elle compte sur nous pour qu'on s'en souvienne.
Say that I'm crazy or call me a fool
Si vous approchez, je vous dirai tout
Enjoy your visit, Héctor.
Bonne visite, Hיctor.
But last night it seemed that I dreamed about you
Cette nuit j'ai rךvי Que j'יtais avec vous
-Papa! -Coco!
- Papב ! - Coco !
When I opened my mouth what came out was a song
J'ai voulu vous parler J'ai choisi une chanson
And you know every word and we all sang along
Celle que vous connaissez Comme une tradition
To a melody played on the strings of our souls
C'est une mיlodie Pleine de souvenirs cachיs
And a rhythm that rattled us down to the bone
Son rythme est le reflet de la vיritי
Our love for each other will live on forever
Et je sais que pour toujours Nous vivrons cet amour
In every beat of my proud corazon
Chante avec moi, ma fiertי corazףn
Our love for each other will live on forever
Je sais que pour toujours Nous vivrons cet amour
In every beat of my proud corazon
Chante avec moi, ma fiertי corazףn
A y mi familia Oiga mi gente
Ay mi familia Oiga mi gente
Canten a coro Let it be known
Canten a coro Parlez-moi d'eux
Our love for each other will live on forever
Je sais que pour toujours Nous vivrons cet amour
In every beat of my proud corazon
Chante avec moi, ma fiertי corazףn
A y mi familia Oiga mi gente
Ay mi familia Oiga mi gente
Canten a coro Let it be known
Canten a coro Parlez-moi d'eux
Our love for each other will live on forever
Je sais que pour toujours Nous vivrons cet amour
In every beat of my proud corazon
Chante avec moi, ma fiertי corazףn